...the which can hello everybody work here a bill the twenty fifty
...by name is seth juarez I'm pretty excited because we
are building some cool stuff for developers to take advantage
of all around the world in fact we have some people here watching for
budapest everyone say hello to budapest caroline the united states...that's right
...I don't know-how many hours they are...but we also...and overhear
...cairo...swatting.
...go so I will tell you we're supposed to have scott got freon we went a little
long you had to take off but we...right now...
Architect new windows server and the system center datacenter products
excellence so what are we going to talk about today what's the thing that's exciting that we're...about,
yeah, so, nano server...I got a great talk about nail server tomorrow nano server is
a new exciting head list deployment option for server now why is that interesting,
yeah, and, the answer is because it's like twenty times smaller than windows server core
all server core was already smaller than server with a
...server is twenty times smaller...pleasure when your nano serve
...thinking like you can put it on it is it like a regular server that
you installer hasn't work,
yeah, absolutely, yeah, it's just because...small doesn't mean it's low-power
...okay so yes you can put on these very small devices in fact that's what we're going to show
...one running on a very small device but also runs on the very largest a
servers so small is really about the cloud
god ok so what I'd like to tell people is...windows has been ...
dominant enterprise operating system they used to be a statement about the
desktop right at some point we said we're going to be the enterprise server right and people
...say what...windows...you defining user experience is a blue screen of
death and want me to believe that that's going to be a great enterprise server and yet today of you
knows but seventy percent of all servers build this year we'll end up with server
on it paid off so what that means is we're able to make that transition
nudge great except now the world's moving to that clout right so there
...of the world's largest cloud services
bing as your office are running on windows server just the statement
of fact that today most startups are not choosing windows as their first choice in
cloud operating systems my jobs to fix that are hand I'm going to and,
that's what...servers all about fantastic so nano server than is
just a smaller footprint os is that what it is well it's
...os optimized for the cloud icy and what does that
...for developer what I put stuff on...what kind of software what so,
to begin with nana service focused in on to scenario of the
first is cloud os infrastructure ok so this is the fabric that you're going to run the
cloud on so think of clustered hyper visor and clustered storage
...infrastructure components the second scenario is the developer scenario
...and that is...the cloud applications so nano server provides them
a very small very lightweight environment to run things where the maximal
resources are applied to their application not the os so
just as for instance nano server consumes one-half the amount of
kernel memory as server core all that's amazing so you have more space to do
you're crazy applications exactly okay and if you
trying to run your applications on a server you can run more the
...on that server guided so why don't you do...you tell us contrast
sort of doctor versus nano...that's a good...so,...a way to think
about it developers are going to get in front of their developers...tool of choice visual
studio and they're going to decide what type of application they want to run which set of
which target they want and that's going to be server or nano server now
just to be clear nano server is a version of server so it's
api compatible for all the api and functions that are available on it but,
there is no gooey stack right there's no when thirty-two compatibility
no while sixty-four and, there's no msi...so you...to pick do I want to
run against full server which is focused in on
sort of compatibility or do I want to target...applications
...target nano server even build your applications visual studio will
say hate that api is not available here et-cetera and then you do a...now you got your
exes now where do you deploy it and the answer is you can deploy it on a
physical machine ok in a virtual machine and...so that's the way you think
...containers are just the way to run applications and
containers can run full server applications or nana server application
icy so is there so what is a difference between deploying something on
a nano server versus a regular services obviously there's
very something's missing what's missing and how can I learn about that, yeah,
so, the key things are the...stack and billy's on servers not a good idea
...long been telling people you get your...them off the server
I don't think people really had an appreciation for how much that gui on a survey class
...it does well twenty x smaller so the...stack is not
there at additionally there isn't any thirty two-bit support
so we work with some of our partners goal hate not get off thirty-two big-gun
...want that took them like a couple hours...pretty straightforward...the compilers some,
yeah, and, then there's no microsoft side so guess what that all that story about
clean-up your installation now you gotta clean-up your...and that's and that's right because what it does
is in the cloud you don't want to have a model where you have
this precious little server the veered the same about pets and cattle no I haven't
...develops guys have a phrase they say well the difference between sort of enterprise model
and cloud model is difference between paths and cattle you want to treat
...servers not like paths where you give them a name...you bring empathic
...you care you want treated like cattle you give
...tag their years and give them a number if something goes wrong you just get rid of it and
get another one it's all about mass management so that's really what we're going for is a dev
...style of management so you manage it with desired stay configuration partial
...configuration for creation you automation you participate in
a dev ops workflow so you'll see will give demonstrations
of nano server being provision using chef that's cool, yeah,
quizzical so let's talk about the devices that you can you put, for example,
nano on a small device like raspberry...no raspberry pie is isn't adam
device...server does not the support adam at this point okay so it's
x eighty-six only...sixty four-bit only but,
yes, you can get very small x...like sixty four-bit
x eighty-six devices but also runs on the very largest so we showed that we
showed nail server running on I think a hundred sixty course server hp server with a terabyte
of ram and we had a thousand
ibm's running on that side and we're only using ten percent of the memory holy cow
...crazy here's the thing so what I hear nano
for some reason I'm thinking like devices but when you say nano you mean this
is a small footprint os that's just like a workforce
...to jag whatever kind of stuff so tell me about have you done some experiments on the
kind of throughput are the kind of sort of
gains you get by using nano instead of the full stack...os,
yeah, so, mostly those gains are in the area of things like installation so
...a...of a server cortex like three hundred seconds in a nano server it
takes forty seconds so talk about agile also in the area
ofsecurity and service ability so again in the cloud you don't
...have to be patching
...especially in the like the cloud fabric so imagine you got a host that you have
the patch you gotta do something with those vans if you have to do a reboot gotta move them off if you have
live migration or you have to shut them all down and restarting if you don't have like migration anyway so
what we did was we analyzed all the patches that windows server talk in two thousand
and fourteen...said how would these apply to nano server here's what we found
that's clever only one out of ten of the critical patches applied
to nana server because they're...orient going related craft stuff,
yeah, the second was it translated into one-quarter the number of
reboot so for times fewer reboot and...since I really I really
like the idea of saying look my application is king here I want to run
...say, for example, can you run like a small case server and run
...dot net on their using core dot net core yes that's exactly what we're
...so now you have the ability to say my website
is important I don't care about any window or anything or any I don't need...I can been
deploy that you can literally scale this thing to hewitt proportion using out server,
yeah, exactly well that's all part of the harvard is you should
only incur the you should only have the components that you need to get your job done
...anything that's installed that isn't directly supporting your job getting done
resources being consumed
...security exposure service ability liabilities that...
don't help you don't have them that's awesome so is there a place where people can download this and look
at it is going to go lives...yes it's going to be available in the next preview of windows server and
...when we're given that out this week or next week pretty darn soon okay well that we're going to have
it available on as your as well all right we'll play with their make sure we get some questions
and because this is...is pretty good ...have any questions coming in all right so
let's put the questions up on the screen so I could take a look at them but I have a couple of other questions
...so we talked about running the
...dot net core down on the nano server what other applications have you seen?
So, where early days but we're working with people and it's going pretty well so we've got
...that...work with the ios team...what I'm going to show casey
getting a little hand here they don't tell anyone fidelity...is embargo, yeah,
until next till tomorrow which?
...of chef which runs on using ruby
...provisioning engine...and...go on top of engine
acts as a nano server that's really cool we do have some questions daniel
asks how do we manage the nano server is there a dashboard
...because there's no more like gui to manage stuff how do you manager, yeah,
so, there's two answers first is remote...work okay we like
the glad people think because I'm the father our...think...every doesn't like goes I love
...I just don't...my server throws things off the server so
gooey belong on the client so all...you do remote management
...server manager works against nano
server a bunch of the remote administration tools work against that
...noise session tomorrow I'm going to show us where...show tomorrow if I don't show tomorrow definitely showed
...ignite...we have a new web-based way to do things that using
...clever...the as your portal and...gorgeous you believe this thing a
lot of times people said well, hey, that's great...great story but, you know, there's
this tool this tomb this tool don't really work well remotely those the tools
...tools we're working on and...shown up in the web browser so device
manager device manager shows up in the web browser that's really cool
I love I love the idea of because I'm...software guy
right and whenever someone says hey I got a set up a server of this like taken and someone else do that
because then you got...server...going to take forever so then what you can do with
...services sort of...a little-bitty thing running your applications,
yeah,...I'll...way...it of...to automation right you do keep the other weighted more the
...way to do it is our shall and desired state configuration is one of the
...key principles of the cloud is you want configuration
as cold right so you don't necessarily want to go to that machine and make it a special
pap what-you want-to do is you want to say here's my configuration I check in
...a text file value checked into source code control if you want to
make a change you check it out you do this you take a look at
it when you're happy and we checked back in and then we deploy it if something goes wrong like
...that was the wrong thing to do guess what we do we go back to
source code control get the previous version say uses one instead so that's that kind
of kelp cattle management mindset icy so what facilities
this nano server have like, for example, let's just say I want to start my own sort of
vm server farm...nano...what is the easiest and best way to all
basically it works with all the same...tools it's just a windows server tool
...version of windows server so hyper...work w ds is going
to work the system centers going to work got it all right so keep your questions
coming about nano server it's a really interesting technology so you
said something interesting and I must admit I don't use it as much as I would like
...you said something about how we're chef tell me what did you do for our...or what is your
role our...and what is it for those that haven't...
ok so our shell is an automation distributed automation environment for
...was the inventor our shell wax?
Look, at there's like...sparks coming out right now that's great, yeah,
...that really means is I hired a great team and behaving the room to do that the best work that's
fantastic so,
what are the kinds of things you can do with our...maybe a better question is
what are the things you can't do let's start with what you can what kind of things to do with our so, yeah,
...although the deserving you can't do...yet though that's the great our of
our shell is that it can do everything we what we trying...is we
...deliver world of high-level task-oriented abstractions we just think about
what you want typing get it but if you can't do that then partial as the ability to
everything you can go down and talked all the dot net api you
...to...you can talk to wi...do p invokes you can do everything within our
...yet but again it's all about trying to create an environment of high-level task-oriented
abstractions now the interesting thing is our shell desired state configuration
...a new model it's more of a declarative approach that basically says
...all-star...righty...cards there and said here's the way I want the world make
...but...desired...is you declare the way you want the world
...and say make itself and then we take
that model and we go make it so in the world I see so I views our
...for loads up it looks like a very...dasi
kind of command thing but it's also a scripting language what kind of languages, yeah, exactly correct
is a combination of an interactive host in descriptive language so think of it
is schumer...dessert topping in a
...together...we have some more questions coming in ram
...says will there be versions of sequel server that...nano server that's a really
good question nothing to announce today but watch that space statehood
...so sasha is the nano server version the one that will be running on
to-you devices I ask you a little bit about that for yet...so is,
you know, we're all based upon...common code base so it's a common code base and a bunch
of the things that we did benefited the imc...bunch of things cat
...benefit us but at this point no it's a separate skew god ok I
...says what about why since in nano server so the way to think about neo
server...deployment option for regular server
...edge windows server skews and then you can install it with server
core or with server with the gui are with small business essentials or
with nano server guy then again you get standard and datacenter and...that all with us
...so there's more questions you guys roll it up slowed down a little bit so I can see it
but they're getting to...so here's another question so?
With nano server is
just look at the server and say we don't need this we don't need that what can we take out is that how it
went I'm curious about the thought process that went around for building annals server,
yeah, so, basically it's the it's the kind of ground-up so we
...and say hey what are the things we need for this environments
...start off very small as we said well here's a scenario that we
...then effectively were page defaulting in the api...start off with nothing
right and then you effectively page fault in based on the scenarios
...what things to bring in so often that would require us to do
big refactoring I should tell you this is not been easy pride always
...expend on for years and years and many years
...I...say we're just delighted that we can finally talk about it because...say these engineers
...working on this for a very long-time it's like working from the ground-up
from the top-down at the same time and try to make sure you meet that sweet spot of the
function either...from a server getting rid of the footprint
that you dull and it's important to note that line of what is...is not a fixed line
yet so as we go we work with say the chef guys to get it re
factored in working on...we found here's a couple api that they need and
...we go on we'll get those api so as we work with each one of the teams are finding out
have we found the right thing here's a question does nano service support all
...existing web application
...so what's the boundary yes so currently
we work with asp what we focused in on is asp dot net the five okay
...news stuff,
yeah, exactly...we will not have the full dot net running
on now server what pro is so it's like I usually think of this is different profiles,
yeah, what profile would be running on...or what is it
...dot net run-time that will be on it's the core clr version got it so what we
...dot net core dot net core dot net core runs on nano server not the full one of
the called the desktop profile where there's others a full dot net...client profile
is the full...there's tons of different flavors but if you're running if you're running on the next
stuff of...sounds like it's...work...yeah, absolutely yes all right so here's some more questions
...run features and roles like a dns server inside
a container on nano so...so let me go back and be clear about what I said okay
the first version of nano server is focused in on to scenario
...os infrastructure that literally means hyper
v and storage and clustering got it and then
...in the cloud applications so here working to get all the interesting language runtime esp
...csharp
ruby javascript java python php getting all those
two-run that environment that stage one over the course of time?
H nano server will be the foundation of server and you'll be able
to install additional roles on top of it...clever so in essence
...os becomes like this big puzzle you have the most important part if you want to
add some more stuff around it you'll be able to do that exactly so we're learning some of our lessons when we did
server core so we did server core we were very clear about what it
was supposed to be basically said this is the server...you should use everybody should be
audit and we did that it was hard to have very clear conversations around
camera talk-to-you-later but you I need you to refactoring code right now
...so allowed us to
get pointing here's a scenarios therefore I know what success and failure looks like and therefore I
managing appropriate liza and then we'll go and expanded to the next round and the next round
...the next as a programmer I've always found that better make something
that works then make it better exactly and that's...so there's more questions are there any our
shell...available now from nano sounds like that ok
...talk about our shelf so because our shows based on dot
net the full dot net is not available on nana server right so we have a new version
of our shell based upon...all that's awesome and
...yes so this was actually quite a bit of work so, we have that up and running most of
the language features are available inrunning now and then we're
working on a very long tail of commandments to get up and running but they'll be certain things that won't
be there in particular windows workflow will not be available okay, yeah,
that's not full...exactly that's not so much of a problem because as a as
a managed element you don't have to run workflow
...you can run workflow on another machine and it can participate in the workflow
...due to the magic of our show promoting okay we have full our shoulder
molding ...got and, then a new set of commandments in fact part of this is a
...of things that we wanted to
do empower shall we said of because there was always the ability to artie p
...and do something and say well that's a really important thing to do but there's an alternative to
ship is to choose let's do these fiji with nano server there is no
...logged on none zero
...matter...enough so that means is it forces us to make sure and go
back and say we have to have full and complete hundred-percent remote
manageability so what that means now I can do remote file editing overpower
shell I can do remote file transfer overpower shell?
...I can do remote debugging overpower...so...literally become caddo,
yeah, exactly that's amazing...right so there's some more questions will there be a need to
modified existing apps to work...almost certainly yes
ok so that's the way you should think about it now we'll have these things called reversed
forwards that allow certain level of application compatibility and we
have use those and be able to bring things over but really the right way to do it is to sit and
read target for this environment it sounds like...targeting for that environment anyways it's going
to make your application leaner and better because it's going to work
in a better faster environment right so more questions
will nano server support doctor images like sky...presented earlier
...yes absolutely although not initially which...next week okay so they'll come
...the release after that but containers...two forms of
containers and what goes into them are two forms of our...unfortunate everything's about
...there's two types of containers is windows server containers and this hyper
...containers...one is more isolated more secure than the
other and then in those containers go-to thanks?
Server or nano server icy all
thanks so much for spending time with us I...impromptu but nano server seems like
a really interesting thing thanks for coming by hopefully we'll see more...tomorrow at
...please stop by thanks for watching we'll get to at the next session.